we received a few questions through
various mediums it's it's sort of common
thing as well people want they're hard
to start practicing what is the best way
to begin your practice say you're just
interested in Buddhism you read
something that you found inspirational
so how do you go about it I think it
should be probably more like something
for beginners to listen to well the
important thing is you don't stop you
don't stop reading you don't stop
learning about the actual suitors and
what the Buddha said you know there are
whole different layers of understanding
to it in a sense that first time you
read a suit they will be inspired it
makes sense and so on but then if you
keep the practice going and then you get
back to the suit at some later stage you
get more out of it you realize that your
previous understanding was correct but
now you just kind of went even a step
further so within the original
understanding you know understood more
and that's kind of inevitable a let let
you let you think that why stop there so
if if next time you come back to it it's
a good chance you'll find even more in
the same suit them so it's important to
recognize that you can never know too
much in terms of the Buddhist
instruction the more you know the
greater likelihood if you're applying
yourself correctly as well with the
proper basis of virtue and so on so the
more you know the greater likelihood is
that you will get to discern those
things within your experience because
you have obviously a wider range of
tools that you can then recognize as
opposed if you just have one so it's
important to to practice learning but in
order for those things to apply sense
restraint in virtue you need to be fully
established so that'sthat's like the
main point really you know often people
differentiate between the clay person in
the monk
and yeah that there's a difference in
terms of the in external statement and
the lifestyle but really the difference
is where the person lives with with
sensuality or without centrality whether
he lives with with sense desires or he
practice a sense restraint in regard to
that's where the difference is so most
commonly as a lay person the person who
lives with sensuality and usually monks
are the ones practicing restraint but
it's important to this to recognize this
to differentiate this because see if
somebody stays a lay person for whatever
reason they they have their does not
automatically mean you should not
practice sense restraint but it is
somehow taken in in that sort of
intentionally ambiguous manner whereby
oh I cannot be a monk because I have to
look after my mother and by default that
means I can also engage a sensuality
because I have a good reason to not be a
mark well it's completely wrong thinking
basically and it's a it's a the two
separate things whether you you want to
pursue a lifestyle of a monk or
lifestyle a person that's one decision
now you make another decision on top of
it to not practice sense restraint or to
practice it only practice it only
partially that has nothing to do with
your choice of being a layman so you're
responsible for basically confusing
these things and then obviously acting
out of sensuality towards it and saying
somebody can become a monk and then
expect the circumstance in the
environment to do the restraint for him
and make no effort internally to uproot
and charlatan on the level of the mind
so although they are not engaging in
sensual activities with their body
they're still very much within
essentially so they're basically living
almost like like like a lay person who
is not restrained and that's also
another reason why this is able to
differentiate is because yes there were
suitors with the good was with will a
lay people understood the Dhamma but
they did not understand the dumb on
account of the sensual life they might
have whenever they stayed a lay person
and not gone forth out of faith in the
in Buddhist teaching that they acquired
he was always rooted in some some
necessity like they they had to look
after their children or the mother they
would die if they leave so it wasn't
even like oh they'll be upset with me no
it's like if if I'm not there looking up
they're done so they had like protecting
other people's lives basically that's
why they couldn't do it but then they
were practicing as laypeople that they
did not take my duty towards my family
or or whatever to be the excuse that I
can also live a sensual life so if you
want to understand the Dhamma you need
to live withdrawn from sensuality and
that is easy to do if you are not a lay
person but if you choose to be a labor
so means you're adding to yourself
another extra task on top of the task of
understanding Dhamma which is sense
restraint amidst the environment that's
completely opposite of the sense
restraint and that's why it's very hard
to sustain that and that's why people
who then tend to avoid or turn a blind
eye to the fact that they're responsible
footage choice off of their environment
more or less and then just go with it go
with it and if people think that five
precepts are enough to practice the
Dharma well those were not really enough
even back in the Buddhist day the Buddha
told the five priests if two people not
as a basis of understanding the like
right view but more as a basis of
differentiating human from an animal
basis of good rebirth basis of eventual
wisdom through that the initial sense
restraint so if you have people who
don't even keep the Five Precepts
and hope they can practice them or have
a view that they are practicing Dhamma
at the same time that is simply
impossible that's after contradiction in terms so
that's after contradiction in terms so
sense restraint is not it's not optional
it's just not optional so you can choose
to be whatever you like but you cannot
choose to be restrained or not and think
you can practice Dhamma the same time or
rather you can choose it but you will be
living a contradiction so whenever the
people who are not monks understood the
Dhamma back in the day it's because they
were withdrawn from sensuality and even
if they decided to go back to sensuality
afterwards it has to be done at the
expense of the practice so you cannot
practice and be in sensuality at the
same time you might be content with what
you understood and they're not made
further effort
as people who get complacent and that
was happening given to the monks in the
suitors and that's when the Buddha would
urge or even tell them off quite
severely almost like verbally abused
them because he said I I know that you
can do it it was to venerable Ananda
when he said that I will not treat you
like a like a Potter treats his precious
clay pot you know I'll smash you with
stone verbally so to speak and then the
the solid core will stand that test
why because I know there was sort of
postponing the work that he still needed
to do you already had the right view but
he was distracting himself with
seemingly important duties such as
sewing robes and getting together with
the monks and teaching him this and
doing that and then they would have
really really told him off so yes you
can get complacent with with your
attainment but in order to develop the
attainment you cannot start from the
complacency as in I am fine as I am in
whatever environment him and sensuality
is not a problem for me
that's just impossible sensuality is
always a problem because it's a direct
contradiction to the principles of the
Dhamma that needs to be understood so
you can't have it both ways and that's
like that that suta were the two friends
go go to the Monte 100 states at the
bottom the other one climbs up and
shouts back down to this one and says
like wow the view from here and I see
all these pools and Gardens and I and
the man from below says no I don't see
any of that now I I disagree with you I
you know you know what you're saying is
wrong and then the man comes down grabs
him by the arm and dragged him back up
and shows him that same view and this is
all yes truly look at these beautiful
delightful sights and so on so the point
is you have to recognize that your
criteria for what is right what is
possible is not necessarily correct
because you might be well at the bottom
of the mountain you're refusing to climb
for whatever reason and then refusing to
climb for whatever reason you use an
excuse to indulge me whatever it's at
the bottom of that mountain and again it
doesn't matter whether you wear robes or
not matters whether you accept
sensuality on the mantle
whether you physically be drawn from it
and whether you're practicing sense
restraint for the point of for the goal
of overcoming it so that's why I said
many times in other talks you need to
take responsibility for your choices
because otherwise you won't feel
responsible for engaging sensuality
because you don't you don't you haven't
taken the responsibility for choosing to
not climb the mountain in terms of the
practice not to go into higher
environment that's fine but that now
means you have to be twice as careful at
the bottom of the mountain not oh
because I'm not at the top of the
mountain I can fully indulge and engage
with whatever comes my way here at the
bottom of the mountain
as I said that's a completely separate
thing that's a completely another extra
layer on top of all it is something
which is already a compromise so you
start a practice by learning and then
you start a practice by fully
integrating and realizing that there is
absolutely no chance of understanding
anything that's been learned unless
there is a proper virtue developed
proper establishment proper sense
restraint and that means celibate
that means moderation and restraint in
eating and and that more more often than
not that doesn't mean only five precepts
5 precepts will make a good person and
by basically 5 precepts are not
negotiable basis for a human life so if you don't
basis for a human life so if you don't
want to be like an animal mentally have
a mind of an animal 5 precepts are the
threshold below which you cannot go and
yes they will offer an improvement to an
unrestrained mind but if you really want
to understand the Dhamma dissin design
of the your mind the necessary condition
for SOTA body for the right view he
needs to be more the mind needs to be
fully be drawn from that sensuality
needs to be celibate needs to be not not
entertained things throughout the day of
central nature if you can sustain that
level in the environment of the you know
outer world at the bottom of the
mountain that's fine but it's it was
hard to sustain back in the Buddhist day
without all the quick instantaneous
access to destroy
and so on and today it's gonna take some
serious willpower and if you were to
possess their willpower and there would
be nothing binding you to the bottom of
the mountain anymore you would overcome
it and go to a better place and even
back in the day as I said you know like
a coffee cut reporter who was on our
Nogami yeah they were not an economist
because sorry they were not celibate
because they were on a gummies
they became on a gum because it was
celibate laid people but celibate and
the only reason he didn't go forth with
the previous Buddha was because he was a
elderly parents they would die without
him they were completely dependent on
him and same the lady I forgot her name
whose son got falsely imprisoned and
murdered she said her composure did not
change and while her husband was alive
before that when she understood the
Dhamma you know she was a dutiful wife
and everything else but he passed away
and then she was just a fully celibate
withdrawn mentally from sensuality
became monogamy establish yourself in
Gianna's and all that so yes you can be
a layperson and and have all the genres
and stuff if you're fully celibate and
we drawn from sensuality and that's I
say usually the people have problem with
this is because for them automatically
it's implicit that I have a good reason
to be labor so which means I'm justified
in engaging with sensuality not at all
not at all so learn practice sense
restraint obviously you have to be draw
yourself to some extent from company and
environment and then things things in
the suit is that seemingly sound like
some old folklore stories and stuff will
definitely start making more and more
sense and you will be very very
verifying it for yourself because your
liability to suffering will be
diminishing